听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
本节 我们将带大家浏览一遍
Now, in this section, I'm going to walk you through the entire Raft consensus algorithm
Raft共识算法实现全序关系广播的完整流程
for performing total order broadcast.
我这里要给出一个警告
Now, I'm going to warn you.
这是一个相对比较复杂的算法
It's a rather complex algorithm.
这是我们在本课程中学习的最复杂的算法
It's by far the most complex algorithm we will see in this course.
介绍整个算法的伪代码需要9页幻灯片
It takes 9 slides of pseudocode to explain the whole algorithm.
我不期待大家能完整记住这个算法
And I'm not expecting you to memorize it all.
我希望大家可以认真理解
What I would like you to do though is to carefully understand
算法的工作原理及其背后的原因
exactly how and why the algorithm works,
因为我发现 理解Raft算法的工作原理
because I find that the principles of how the Raft algorithm works
对于理解分布式系统中的状态具有很强的启发意义
are really instructive for thinking about state in a distributed system more generally.
我们开始吧
OK, so, let's start.
Raft算法的核心是一个状态机
The core of the Raft algorithm is a state machine,
每个节点可以处于三种状态之一：从节点、候选节点、主节点
where every node can be in one of three states, either a follower, a candidate, or a leader.
每个任期只可能有一个状态
And the state is always in a certain term.
系统包含一个特定的任期数
So, there's always a certain term number,
一个节点可以在特定的任期内成为主节点
and a node can be the leader in a particular term.
当一个节点第一次启动时 它总会进入从节点状态
When a node starts up for the first time, it always goes into the follower state.
如果一个节点崩溃并随后恢复
And also, if a node crashes and recovers,
当此节点重启 并从崩溃状态恢复后
and then when the node restarts and recovers from the crash,
无论此节点在崩溃前处于什么状态
it always goes back into the follower state,
它都会回到从节点状态
regardless of which state it was in before the crash.
然而 所有节点启动时都是从节点
However, all of the nodes start as followers,
但我们最终总需要让一个节点成为主节点
eventually, we need some node to become the leader.
节点想要成为主节点 首先要成为候选节点
And the way how a node becomes the leader is by first becoming a candidate.
当一个节点检查到
And so, when a node detects that
已经有一段时间没有从主节点收到消息了 已经出现了超时情况
there has been no message from a leader for some amount of time, a timeout elapses,
那么此节点将决定
and then a node will decide that,
在这一特定任期内 我可以站出来 成为候选节点
OK, it is going to stand as candidate in a particular term number.
在这一任期数内 它将尝试从其他节点处得到选票
And within that term number, it's going to try to get votes from the other nodes.
如果它能得到系统中大多数节点的选票
And if it manages to get positive votes
即多半quorum节点为此节点投票
from a quorum of nodes in the system, from a majority,
则这个节点就能够转变为主节点状态
then it is able to transition into the leader state.
然而 也可能出现的一种情况是 在此次选举过程中
However, it could also happen that in the process of this election,
候选节点发现另一个节点有更高的任期数
the candidate discovers that there's a different node with a higher term number.
如果发生了这种情况 则候选节点将立即退回为从节点
And if it does, so, then the candidate immediately steps back becomes follower again,
并与拥有更高任期数的节点一同工作
and works with the node that has the higher term number.
也就是说 更高任期的优先级总是更高
So, a higher term number always takes precedence.
当节点处于候选节点状态时 还可能出现另一种情况
It could also happen while a node is in the candidate state.
节点参与了选举 但是节点当前
It's doing the election, but maybe it's not able to
无法与足够多的quorum副本或quorum节点通信
communicate with a quorum of replicas right now, or quorum of nodes.
因此 选举超时了
And so, it times out.
此节点在规定时间内无法收到quorum节点足够数量的选票
So, it simply doesn't receive a quorum of positive votes within the required time.
如果出现了这种情况 此节点将用更高的任期数重启选举
And if, so it will restart its election again with a higher term number.
也就是说 此节点仍然为候选节点状态 用更高的任期数重启选举
So, it remains candidate and starts again with a higher term number.
同样地 主节点在执行主节点的工作时 还可能发生一种情况
Likewise, it could happen if the leader is just doing its leadering job.
主节点发现系统中出现了一个持有更高任期数的节点
It might discover that there's a node with a higher term number.
可能系统出现了网络分区 一些子集节点
Perhaps the system has been partitioned so that some subset of nodes
在这一时期已在更高的任期数下选举出了新的主节点
have elected a new leader with a higher term number in the meantime.
如果该主节点发现了某个持有更高任期数的其它节点
And if so, the leader will always step back and become a follower again immediately
则该主节点将立刻重新退回到从节点状态
upon discovering some other node with a higher term number.
Raft算法总存在一个非常和平的权力转换过程
So, we always have a very peaceful transition of power in the Raft algorithm
让系统从低任期数转变到高任期数
from the lower term number to the higher term number.
让我们来看一下实际的代码
So, let's run through the actual code.
我们先从初始化变量开始
And so, here we start off with the usual initialization of variables.
我不会现在就讲解每一个变量的作用
I'm not going to explain every single variable right now,
当算法使用了某个变量时 我才会讲解此变量的作用
but I will explain the variables as we use them as part of the algorithm.
我这里想指出的是
But I will just point out here,
currentTerm（当前任期）、votedFor（投票给）
the first four variables currentTerm, votedFor,
log（日志）和commitLength（确认长度）
log and commitLength,
这前四个变量必须存储在持久存储器中 即存储在硬盘中
these four variables have to be stored in stable storage, that is, on disk,
而后面五个变量
whereas the remaining five variables,
可以存储在易失存储器中 即我们允许这些变量在节点崩溃时丢失
they can be in transient storage, they can be lost in the case of a crash.
但前四个变量在节点崩溃时必须能保存下来
But the first four variables have to be preserved in the case of a crash.
你可以看到这里的崩溃恢复部分
And you can see the crash recovery here.
在崩溃恢复时 后面的五个变量
So, those the five remaining variables simply get reset to new fresh states
可以被简单重置为初始化状态
if we recover from a crash.
现在 我前面说过 当一个节点怀疑主节点已失效时
Now, as I said, when a node suspects that the leader has failed,
它将成为候选节点 并启动选举 这就是下面这部分代码的工作
it will become a candidate, and it will start an election. That's what happens here.
顺带一提
By the way, typically,
节点怀疑主节点已失效的超时时间是随机选取的
this timeout that the node uses before it suspects a leader to have failed is randomized.
这么做的目的是避免大量的节点
And the purpose for that is to avoid having lots of nodes
在同一时刻尝试成为候选节点
all trying to become candidate at the same time,
如果所有节点设置了相同的超时时间 在相同的时间启动选举
which is what would happen if all the nodes start up at the same time,
就可能发生这种情况
and then have the same timeout before they start an election.
随机化超时时间
So, randomizing the timeout
可以降低同一时刻启动多个选举的发生概率
reduces the probability of having several elections at the same time.
总之 如果节点怀疑主节点超时 此节点会决定启动选举
So, whenever that happens now, so, the node decides it's time to start an election.
它会递增currentTerm
It increments the currentTerm.
它将currentRole（当前角色）设置为候选节点状态
It sets its currentRole to be the candidate state.
就像正常的选举一样 每个人都会在选举中为自己投票
And like in every good election, everyone votes for themselves in an election.
Raft也是如此
So, also in Raft.
刚刚成为候选节点的节点也会为自己投票
So, the node that has just become a candidate votes for itself
投票方法是将votedFor（投票给）变量设置为自己的nodeId（节点id）
by setting this votedFor variable to its own nodeId.
这里还有一个nodeId集合
And it has this set of nodeId
这个变量会记录此节点收到的、支持自己作为主节点的选票
in which it records the set of votes that it has received in favor of itself as a candidate.
它将自己的nodeId先添加到votesReceived（已收到选票）集合中
And it puts its own nodeId as the first member of that set of votesReceived.
变量lastTerm（上一任期）被初始化为0
This variable, lastTerm, is initially 0,
但你可以看到 如果log.length>0 我们就要设置lastTerm变量
but you can see if log.length>0, then we set this lastTerm variable.
让我先来解释一下什么是log（日志）
So, let me explain first what the log is.
右上角给出了示意图 log是一个数组或一个列表
So, the log, you can see illustrated up here, is an array or a list.
log按顺序存储了一系列log项
It's a sequence of log entries.
每个log项都包含两个部分
Each log entry consists of two parts.
第一部分是消息（msg）
Firstly, a message.
这就是我们希望通过全序关系广播所传递的消息
So, this is the message that we want to deliver via total order broadcasts.
这也是此算法的最终目的
That's the whole thing that the purpose of the algorithm.
第二部分是每个log项的任期数（term）
And secondly, a term number on every log entry.
这个任期数是当主节点将特定的log项添加到log中时
So, this term number is the term number of the leader
此主节点所持有的任期数
at the time when that leader added that particular entry to the log.
我们稍后会看到 为什么任期数会如此重要
And we'll see later why that term number is important.
但现在 只需要接受log是这样一个数据结构
But for now, just accept that log is this structure here.
这是一个0为起始索引值的数组 log[0]是第一个log项
It's an 0-indexed array, where log[0] is the first log entry.
log.length是log中包含的log项数量
And log.length is the number of log entries in the log.
如果log非空 即如果log.length>0
And if the log is non-empty here, if the log.length>0,
我们就让lastTerm等于最后一个log项中的任期字段
then we're going to say that the lastTerm is the term field of the last log entry.
log.length-1就是log中最后一项的索引值
So, log.length-1 is the index of the last entry in the log.
因此 我们取出最后一个log项的任期字段
And so, we take the term field of that last log entry,
将此字段的值赋给lastTerm
and set that to be the value of this variable lastTerm.
我们接下来要构造发送给所有节点的消息
And we then construct a message that will be sent to all of the nodes.
候选节点要向所有节点发送相同的消息
And so, the candidate sends the same message to all of the nodes.
此消息的消息类型被标记为VoteRequest（投票请求）
It's a message tagged with the message type VoteRequest,
意思是：“请给我投票”
saying, “Please vote for me.”
此消息包含多个字段
And the message contains the several fields.
包含候选节点的nodeId
It contains the nodeId of the candidate.
包含任期数递增后的currentTerm
It contains the currentTerm after that term number has been incremented.
包含候选节点的log.length
It contains the log.length on the candidate.
消息还包含lastTerm变量
And it contains this lastTerm variable,
我前面说过 此变量等于候选节点log中最后一个log项的任期字段
which as I just said, is the term field of the last log entry in the candidate’s log.
此节点向所有节点发送相同的这一消息
It sends this same message to all of the nodes.
此节点启动计时器
And it starts the timer
如果没有选举成功 则计时器会报告超时
that might eventually time out if it doesn't manage to do the election successfully.
这就是候选节点的行动
So, that's the candidate.
我们来看看
Let's see
当其他节点收到这些VoteRequest消息时会发生什么
what happens on the other nodes that receive one of these VoteRequest messages.
现在 我们是收到候选节点消息的一个其它节点
So now, we're one of the other nodes that has received a message from the candidate.
我们得到了候选节点的id（cId）
And we have the id of the candidate.
我们得到了候选节点的任期数（cTerm）
We have the term number of the candidate,
候选节点的log长度（cLogLength）
the length of the candidate's log,
以及候选节点最后一个log项的任期数（cLogTerm）
and the term number in the candidates last log entry.
当收到VoteRequest消息后 我们要做的第一件事情是
And the first thing we're going to do when receiving a VoteRequest message is
比较cTerm和消息接收方的currentTerm
to compare the cTerm to the currentTerm on of the recipient of this message.
如果cTerm大于接收方的currentTerm
And if the cTerm is greater than the currentTerm of the recipient,
则我们继续前进 加入候选节点的任期
then we move forward and join the term of the candidate.
实现这一点的方法是 将接收方的currentTerm设置为cTerm
So, we do that by setting the recipient's currentTerm to be the cTerm,
无论接收方节点之前的状态是什么 都将节点状态设置为从节点
to transition into the follower state regardless of what the node's previous state was,
同时 把votedFor变量设置为null（空）
and this votedFor variable gets set to null,
意思是 我们还没有在当前任期内给任何候选节点投过票
which means that we have not yet voted for any candidate in the current term,
因为我们刚刚修改了当前任期
because we just changed the current term.
我们随后就会为此节点投票
However, we might vote for that candidate in a minute.
接下来 我们按照和候选节点相似的方式设置变量lastTerm
So, next, we set up this variable lastTerm very similar to the way we did on the candidate.
也就是说 我们查看VoteRequest消息接收方的最后一个log项
And that is, we look at the last log entry on the recipient of this VoteRequest message.
我们得到最后一个log项的任期数 并将其赋值给lastTerm变量
We get the term number in that last log entry, and we set that to be this lastTerm variable.
我们现在要做的是
Now, what we need to do is
检查候选节点的log与我们自己的log相比是不是最新的
to check if the candidate’s log is up-to-date with our own log.
这样做的原因是
The reason for that is that
我们不希望一个持有过时log的候选节点成为主节点
we don't want a candidate with an outdated log to become the leader.
后面大家就会理解什么叫做过时
And exactly what outdated means will become apparent later.
但重要的一点是 我们希望候选节点的log
But it's crucial that we want the candidate’s log to reflect all the updates
至少包含了quorum节点已经持有的log
that at least the quorum of other nodes has seen.
因此 你不能让一个持有过时log的节点成为主节点
So, you don't end up with a leader whose log is really outdated,
因为这意味着我们会丢失很多消息
because that might lead to the loss of some messages.
我们这里的logOk变量是一个布尔值 这个变量告诉我们
So, we have this logOk variable here, which will contain a Boolean, which tells us
当前节点是否认为候选节点的log符合要求 可以给此候选节点投票
whether the current node thinks the candidate's log is OK to vote in favor of.
有两个判断标准
And so, there are two criteria here.
首先 如果候选节点的log任期
First of all, if the log term of the candidate,
即候选节点最后一个log项的任期数
so, the term number that appears in the last log entry of the candidate,
如果此任期数
if that term number is greater than
大于收到VoteRequest消息接收方最后一个log项的任期数
the term number of the log entry on the recipient of this VoteRequest message,
则我们认为候选节点的log符合要求
then we consider the log to be OK.
候选节点的log符合要求的另一个判断标准是
Secondly, another way for the log to be OK is
两个节点最后一个log项的任期相同
for the log term in the last log entry to be the same,
但候选节点持有的log数量
but for the candidates to have a log
至少等于收到VoteRequest消息接收方的log数量
that is at least as long as the log of the recipient of this VoteRequest message.
两个条件满足其中一个就可以 两者选其一
So, one of those things needs to be true, either-or.
如果满足条件 则log符合要求
And if so, then the log is OK.
如果下述三个判断标准成立 则我们要为此候选节点投票
So, we will now vote for this candidate if three criteria will hold.
第一 如果cTerm等于currentTerm
Firstly, if the cTerm equals the currentTerm,
也就是说 任期没有过时
that is, it's not in some outdated term,
我们还未看到任何持有更高任期数的节点
we haven't seen any other node with a higher term number.
第二 如果候选节点的log符合要求
Secondly, if the candidate's log is OK.
第三 如果我们在当前任期还没有给任何其他候选节点投过票
And thirdly, if we have not yet voted for any other candidate in the current term.
如果我们在当前任期还没有给任何其他候选节点投票
So, this votedFor variable would be null
则votedFor应该为null
if we have not yet voted at all for any candidate in the current term,
或者如果我们已经为相同的候选节点投过票 则votedFor为cId
or it could be cId if we've already voted for the same candidate.
在单一任期内 我们允许给相同的候选节点多次投票
It's OK to vote several times for the same candidate in a single term.
但我们在相同的任期内不能给两个不同的候选节点投票
But we must not vote for two different candidates within the same term.
如果这三个判断标准都成立 则我们就可以为此候选节点投票
So, if all those three criteria are true, then we can vote in favor of this candidate.
我们的投票方法是 首先把votedFor变量设置为cId
We will do that by first setting our votedFor variable to cId
记录下我们已经给这个候选节点投过票了
to remember the fact that we have voted for the candidate.
随后 我们给候选节点返回VoteResponse（投票响应）消息
And then, we send a VoteResponse message back to the candidate.
此消息将包含投票节点的nodeId
And this is going to contain nodeId of the node doing the vote.
包含currentTerm的值
It's going to contain the currentTerm number,
这样我们就知道这张选票所处的任期
so, we know which term this election is for.
此消息还包含一个值true 表明这是一张投给此候选节点的投票
And the value true to indicate that it's a vote approval in favor of this candidate.
另一方面 如果任意一个判断标准不成立
On the other hand, if any of those things are not true,
则发送给候选节点的VoteResponse消息会包含false
then we send a VoteResponse with a false field back to the candidate,
告诉它我们没有为此候选节点投票
telling it that we are not voting in favor of this candidate.
现在 我们回到候选节点
Now, we move back to the candidates.
我们要聚合结果 我们要收集收到的选票
And we aggregate. We collect the votes that we receive.
每当我们收到一个VoteResponse消息时 我们按照下述方式处理
So, any time we receive a VoteResponse message, this is what happens.
VoteResponse消息包含了投票方的id（voterId）
So, we have a VoteResponse with the id of the node that is voting,
包含了投票所属的任期（term）
with the term number in which the vote is happening,
包含了一个布尔值（granted） 表示是否为此候选节点投票
and with the Boolean telling us whether that vote is granted or not.
我们要做的第一件事情是检查任期数
And the first thing we do is to check the term number.
如果VoteResponse消息的term大于我们的currentTerm
So, if the term number in the VoteResponse message is greater than our currentTerm,
我们和之前一样处理此消息
we do the usual thing,
我们接受此任期数作为当前任期数
we accept that term number as our own,
我们将自己转变为从节点状态
we transition into follower state,
我们忘记上一个任期我们给谁投的票
we forget which node we voted for in some previous term,
我们取消所有的选举计时器
and we cancel any election timer.
这一系列过程都是把我们的状态机转换为从节点状态
So, that just moves us back into the follow state in the state machine.
然而 如果我们仍然处于候选节点状态
However, if we are still in the candidate state,
并且如果我们收到的消息所属的任期
and if the message that we just received is for the correct term
就是我们在执行选举的正确任期
in which we're performing the election,
并且granted字段的值是true
and the granted field is true,
那我们就得到了一张给候选节点的选票
then we have a vote in favor of us as the candidate.
我们将更新这里的votesReceived集合
So, we're going to maintain this set of votesReceived here.
我们将voterId添加至votesReceived集合中
And we're going to add the id of the voter to the set of votesReceived.
注意 这里的更新操作是幂等的
Notice that this update here is idempotent.
即使VoteResponse消息在网络中被重复传输
So, even if this VoteResponse message gets duplicated in the network somewhere,
这也不是问题 我们不会重复计算相同的选票
that's not a problem, we're not going to count the same vote more than once.
我们仍然要求选票来自于不同的quorum节点
We still require votes from a quorum of different nodes.
接下来 为了判断quorum节点数量是否满足要求
So, then, to determine whether we have a quorum yet,
我们可以检查votesReceived集合的大小
we can check the cardinality of this set votesReceived.
如果我们收到的选票数量大于或等于多半
And if the number of votes we received is greater than or equal to a majority,
也就是说 大于或等于系统中的节点数量加1、除以2、向上取整
that is, the number of nodes in the system plus 1 divided by 2 round upwards,
我们就得到了多半quorum节点的选票
then we have a majority quorum of nodes.
此时 我们就可以成为主节点了 撒花庆祝！
And at that point, we can become the leader, hurrah!
我们转变成主节点状态 currentLeader（当前主节点）就是我们自己
So, we transition to leader state. The currentLeader, well, that's ourselves now.
我们也取消所有的选举计时器
We can cancel the election timer as well.
现在 我们需要给其他所有节点 也就是现在的从节点 发送一条消息
And now, we need to send a message to all of the nodes, which are now the followers,
告诉它们：“大家好 我是你们的新主节点了 给点信息吧”
to tell them, “Hey, I'm your new leader, and give it a bit of information.
这里的REPLICATELOG（复制日志）函数
So, this REPLICATELOG function here
将会发送这条消息
is going to do the actual sending of that message,
我们稍后就会展开介绍此函数
and we will see that function in a minute.
我们还需要让主节点设置和从节点相关的一些变量
We also need to set up for all of the followers some variables.
这些变量是sentLength（发送长度）和actedLength（确认长度）
These variables here, sentLength and actedLength,
它们都将nodeId映射成整数
are maps from nodeId to an integer.
主节点要为每一个从节点初始化这些变量
And so, for each of the follower nodes, we're going to initialize these variables here.
sentLength要设置成主节点的log.length
The sentLength is going to be initialized with the log.length on the leader.
sentLength的意思是
And the meaning of sentLength is
主节点已经向特定从节点发送的log项数量
the number of log records that we have already sent to a particular node.
这里我们假设
So, here we are assuming that
从节点已经从主节点收到了sentLength之前的所有log项
the follower has already received all of the log entries from us.
如果不满足这一假设情况 我们会用后面介绍的一个过程来纠正这一情况
If that is not the case, we will correct that later through a process that we will see later.
第二 actedLength从0开始计数
Secondly, actedLength is the number of log entries, counted from the beginning,
表示此特定从节点已经确认的log项数量
that this particular follower acknowledged as having received.
我们把这个变量初始化为0
And we initialized that to be 0,
随后 当我们收到确认后 我们将递增这个变量
and later, as we receive acknowledgements, we will increase that number.
这就是成为主节点时要做的事情
OK, so that's all we have to do to become a leader.
现在我们有了一个主节点 我们将真正开始讨论全序关系广播了
Now that we have a leader, we can actually start talking about the total order broadcast.
我们现在有一个可以被客户端调用的函数
So, what we have here is now a function that can be called by a client, for example,
这个函数告诉我们：“我们想广播一条消息”
to say, “OK, we want to broadcast a message.”
我们希望通过全序关系广播来广播这条消息
And we want to do that via total order broadcast
保证所有节点按照相同的顺序传递此消息
ensuring that all nodes deliver that the messages in the same order.
消息和消息的传递顺序
Now, the order in which those messages are going to be delivered
就是由log来维护的
is in fact exactly the log.
这就是log的全部作用
That's the whole purpose of the log.
只有主节点能在log中增加log项
And the only node that can add entries to the log is the leader.
我们首先要做的是
And so, first of all, the first thing we have to do is
如果广播一条消息的请求没有发生在主节点处
if the request to broadcast a message happens not on the leader,
则此节点要通过FIFO链路将广播请求转交给当前主节点
then it has to be forwarded to the current leader via a FIFO link.
这里使用FIFO链路的原因是
Using a FIFO link here just ensures that
我们要保证最后实现的是FIFO全序关系广播 而不只是全序关系广播
in total, we actually get FIFO total order broadcast, not just total order broadcast.
实现FIFO全序广播唯一要做的就是通过FIFO链路转交广播请求
And that's the only thing we need to do in order to ensure the FIFO aspect.
如果当前节点是主节点
If the current node is the leader,
我们可能会收到转交过来的消息广播请求
and we may have just received one of those forwarded requests to broadcast a message,
我们首先要做的是 在log中追加一条记录
well, the first thing we do is we append a record to the log
记录中包括我们想要广播的消息（msg）
containing the message that we want to broadcast,
且包括主节点的当前任期数（currentTerm）
and containing the current term number of the leader.
我们也让主节点做个标记 确认自己已经传递了这条消息
We also note that the leader itself has acknowledged the delivery of this message.
这是另一种给自己投票的形式
And that's just another instance of voting for ourselves.
这里的nodId是主节点的id
So, nodeId here is the id of the leader,
因此 我们只需要更新actedLength变量
and so, we're just updating this actedLength variable
让其包含新追加的记录
to include the newly appended record.
现在 主节点向每个从节点再次调用REPLICATELOG函数
And now, we call again this REPLICATELOG function
我们在上一页幻灯片中已经见到过这个函数了
that we already had on the last slide for each of the followers.
主节点要向除自己外的所有节点调用此函数
So, all of the nodes in the system apart from the leader.
此外 我们也要周期性地调用这个REPLICATELOG函数
Moreover, we also call this REPLICATELOG function periodically.
即使主节点没有向log追加任何新的消息
So, the leader, even if it doesn't have any new messages appended to the log lately,
它仍然需要周期性地向每个从节点调用REPLICATELOG
it's still called REPLICATELOG for each of the followers periodically.
周期性调用有几个目的
And that has several purposes.
第一是充当心跳包
One is to act as a kind of heartbeat.
调用REPLICATELOG会向从节点发送一条消息
So, calling REPLICATELOG sends a message to the followers,
告诉它们主节点还活着
just telling them that the leader is still alive.
它们不需要启动新的主节点选举 一切顺利
So, they don't need to start a new leader election. Everything is fine.
调用REPLICATELOG也可以保证 如果任意消息丢失
Calling REPLICATELOG also ensures that
消息还会被重新传递
if any messages got lost, for example, then they will get redelivered.
这也能保证如果主节点提交了任何log项
And it ensures that if the leader has committed any log entries,
那么这些log项也会被从节点提交
then they will also be committed on the followers.
我们稍后会讲解提交过程
The process for committing, we will see later.
我们来看看这个REPLICATELOG函数
So, let's have a look at this REPLICATELOG function
我们已经提到过这个函数三次了
that we've just seen called three times.
REPLICATELOG函数的输入参数是
So, this REPLICATELOG function gets called
主节点的节点id（leaderId）和从节点的节点id（followerId）
first of all, with the node id of the leader, and the node id of the follower.
此函数也能访问之前创建的所有变量
And we have access to all of the variables from before.
首先 我们要将主节点的log拆分为prefix部分和suffix部分
So, first of all, we are going to now split the log on the leader into a prefix and a suffix.
prefix部分将包括
The prefix will contain
主节点认为已经发送给特定从节点的所有log项
all of the log entries that we think we have already sent to the follower.
suffix部分将包括
And the suffix will contain
主节点认为还没有发送给特定从节点的所有新log项
all of the new log entries that we think we have not yet sent to this particular follower.
我们这里设置的变量sentLength
And so, we have this variable sentLength here, which records
记录了我们已经为每个nodeId发送了的log项数量
for every nodeId, the number of log entries that we think we have already sent there.
因此 这里的prefixLen也是一个整数
And so, this prefixLen is just an integer now.
我们将suffix部分设置为
And I'm going to take the suffix of the log
从prefixLen索引值开始 一直到log中的最后一个log项
which is starting at the index prefixLen, and going all the way up to the end of the log,
即prefixLen之后所有剩余的log项
so, all of the remaining log entries after prefixLen.
有可能出现prefixLen就等于整个log的长度
It could happen that prefixLen is indeed the length of the entire log,
这种情况下 suffix部分就是一个空数组
in which case the suffix would just be an empty array.
接下来 我们要设置prefixTerm变量
Next, we set up this variable, the prefixTerm.
我们要找到
And that is now going to be looking at the log entries,
prefix部分中的最后一个log项
we're going to look at the last log entry within the prefix,
查看此log项的任期数
and look at the term number of that log entry.
这与我们之前构造VoteRequest消息时所做的事情很相似
So, this is a bit similar to what we had previously in the VoteRequest message.
此时 我们要查看的不是所有log中的最后一个log项
In this case, what we're looking at is not the last log entry in the log all together,
而是prefix部分的最后一个log项 并得到此log项的任期数
but the last log entry in the prefix, and getting the term number of that.
主节点现在将要向从节点发送一个LogRequest（日志请求）消息
And we're now going to send a LogRequest
消息中包含下述所有变量
with all of these various variables to the follower.
我们要在这条消息中增加主节点的id（leaderId）
So, in this message, we're going to include the id of the leader,
主节点的任期数（currentTerm）
the term number, in which it's the leader,
从节点尚未发送确认信息的prefix部分长度（prefixLen）
the length of the prefix that we are not sending,
prefix部分最后一个log项的任期数（prefixTerm）
the term number of the last log entry in the prefix,
commitLength 我们稍后会了解这个变量的含义 这也是一个整数
the commitLength which is a variable that we will see later, that's just another integer,
以及suffix部分 这是主节点想要在log中增加的新log项数组
and then, suffix, which is this array of new log entries that we want to add to the log.
这就是主节点发送LogRequest消息的方法
OK, so, that was how we send the LogRequest.
我们现在切换到从节点
Now, we're on the followers.
我们来看看从节点如何处理收到的LogRequest消息
And we will see how to receive one of these LogRequest messages.
上面是我们提到的所有变量
So, we've got all of the variables that I just mentioned.
和前面一样 从节点要做的第一件事是检查任期数
And the first thing we need to do as always is to check the term number.
如果消息中的任期数
And so, if the term number in the message
大于从节点的任期数
is greater than the term number on the follower,
则我们和之前一样 更改状态机的状态
then we're going to do the usual state machine thing.
我们将接受新的任期数
We're going to accept the current term.
我们将忘记上一个任期内我们给哪个候选节点投了票
We're going to forget what candidate we voted for in the previous term.
我们取消选取计时器
We’re going to cancel election timer.
我们也会落入第二个判断条件内
And we will also fall through to this second if condition,
我们在这里将currentRole设置为从节点
where we set the currentRole to be follower.
我们接受当前主节点为LogRequest消息的发送方
And we accept the current leader as being the sender of this LogRequest message.
之所以会落入第二个判断条件
So, we fall through to this second case,
是因为这里我们将currentTerm更新为收到的任期数
because here we update currentTerm to equals term.
因此 第二个判断条件中 任期数仍然等于currentTerm
And so, it still equals currentTerm here in the second condition.
这里仍然会有第二个判断条件 因为还可能发生的是
The second condition is also here, because it could happen that
收到LogRequest消息的节点
the node receiving the LogRequest
实际上是在当前任期数内竞争主节点的候选节点
is actually a candidate in the same term number as the leader.
在这种情况下 我们仍然转变成从节点状态
And in that case, we also want to move into follower state.
即使我们没有改变任期数
Even though we're not changing the term number,
我们仍然接受LogRequest消息的发送方为主节点
but we still want to accept the sender of this LogRequest message as the leader.
我们下一件要做的是做另一个检查 验证log是否符合要求
OK, next thing we need to do is do another check if the log is OK.
这有点类似于早些时候主节点选举期间的处理过程
This is a bit similar to what happened earlier during the leader election.
但这里的检查条件有些不一样
But the condition is a little different.
我们在这里首先想要保证的是
So, here, what we first of all want to ensure is
还记得我在前一页幻灯片讲到的
remember we said in on the previous slide,
我们把log分为从节点还没有确认的prefix部分
we split the log into a prefix that we are not sending,
我们假定接收方已经拥有了prefix部分的log项
which we assume the recipient already has,
以及包含新log项的suffix部分
and the suffix, which contains the new log entries.
首先 我们必须检查
Well, first of all, we have to check
从节点prefix部分持有的log项确实是主节点认为我们持有的log项
that prefix we actually do have as the sender of the message thought we might do.
我们首先必须检查从节点的log.length
So, first of all we have to check that the follower’s log.length
log.length至少应该与主节点的prefix部分一样长
is at least as long as the prefix that we left out on the sender.
如果不满足这个条件 则意味着主节点和从节点之间的log项有缺口
So, if this is not the case, that means there would be a gap in the log,
主节点没有给我们发送一些应该已经发送过的log项
where there're some log entries that the leader didn't send us,
从节点没有这些log项
but we also don't have on the follower.
这种情况下 log不符合要求 我们必须先把log项的缺口抹平
And so, in that case, the log would not be OK. We have to fill in that gap first.
第二个要求是 或者prefixLen等于0
The second requirement is either the prefixLen is 0,
或者如果prefixLen不等于0
or if the prefixLen is not 0,
我们查看从节点prefix部分的最后一个log项
then we have to look at the last log entry in the prefix on the follower,
我们希望这个log项的任期数
look at its term number, and we want that term number
等于主节点对应log项的任期数
to be equal to the corresponding log entries term number on the leader.
这里的prefixTerm就是主节点对应log项的任期数 随消息发送了过来
This prefixTerm is just a variable that was sent as part of the message.
这么做的目的是 Raft在执行过程中会保证维持一个不变性
So, the purpose for this is Raft has a certain invariant that it guarantees.
即如果系统中的两个节点在特定索引值上都有一个log项
And that is if there are two nodes in the system that have a certain log,
同时 如果此特定索引值上的两个log项是相同的
and that's at a certain index of the log, they have the same log entry,
特别地 如果这两个log项的任期数是相同的
in particular, they have the same term number in that log entry,
Raft将保证
then, Raft will guarantee that
两个节点到此索引值之前的所有log项也一定相同
the entire log up to and including that index will be identical.
因此 log项的任期数将允许我们很快判断出
So, the term number in the log entries actually allows us to tell efficiently
这两个节点持有的log项是否相同
whether two nodes have the same log or not,
因为两个节点拥有不同log项的唯一方法是
because the only way that two nodes could end up with different logs is
特定log项的任期不相同
by having different term numbers on a certain log entry.
因此 这里要保证的是
And so, what this here now guarantees is that
如果logOk的判断结果为true
if this logOk condition is true,
这意味着主节点prefix部分的log项
that means that the prefix of the log as it was on the leader
与从节点prefix部分到prefixTerm为止的log项完全相同
is identical to the prefix of the log of the same length as it is on the follower.
因此 这里logOk检查的是 到prefixTerm为止的log项是否完全相同
So, this logOk condition checks that actually the up to that point, the logs are identical.
这非常重要
This is absolutely crucial
这可以保证所有节点最终都会按照相同顺序传递相同的消息
for ensuring that actually, all of the nodes end up with the same messages delivered.
现在 如果log符合要求 且如果消息的任期是正确的
Now, if this log is OK, and if the message was for the correct term,
我们将继续前进
then we can go ahead and process the new log entries
处理这条LogRequest消息中包含的新log项
that were in this LogRequest message.
我们的具体处理方法是
And the way we're going to do this is
调用这个APPENDENTRIES（追加项）函数 我稍后会具体讲解这个函数
we're going to call the APPENDENTRIES function that I will show you in a minute.
我们会为函数传入suffix部分 即传入新的log项 并传入其他一些变量
And we're going to pass it the suffix, the new log entries, and a few other variables.
我们还要给主节点发送一个确认（ack）
And we're going to also send an acknowledgement back to the leader,
称：“我已经收到你的log项并处理完毕了”
saying, “Hey, we received your log entries. It's all fine.”
这个确认就是另一个整数
And this acknowledgement is going to be just another integer.
这个整数将告诉主节点
And it's going to be the integers telling
从节点已经从主节点
how many log entries from the start of the log
成功收到的log项数量
that we have successfully received from the leader.
这个整数等于尚未回复确认的数量（prefixLen）
And that is going to be the length of the prefix that was not sent
加上主节点发送的suffix中所包含的log项数量（suffix.length）
plus the number of log entries in the suffix that was sent.
这就是处理完此条消息后
So, that's the total number of log entries
从节点从主节点收到的log项总数量
that we have from the leader after processing this message.
我们将把这个ack整数打包到一条消息中
And this ack integer, we're just going to pack into a message.
我们要创建LogResponse（日志回复）消息 并将其发送回主节点
So, we're going to make a LogResponse message that we sent back to the leader.
这条消息将包含LogResponse消息的发送方id（nodeId）
It's going to contain the id of the sender of LogResponse,
当前任期数（currentTerm）
the current term number as always,
我之前已经解释过ack
the act that I just explained,
以及一个true 表明处理成功
and true to indicate that this was successful.
此时 从节点已经成功处理了这条LogRequest消息
So, the follower was successfully able to process this LogRequest message.
另一方面 如果不满足判断条件
On the other hand, if something is not OK,
即如果任期数是错误的 或者logOk为false
so, if the term number is wrong, or if the logOk is false,
则从节点发送回一条LogResponse消息 其最后一个变量为false
then we send back a LogResponse message in which the last element is false.
这将告诉主节点
And that tells the leader that
从节点无法成功处理这条LogRequest消息
we were not able to process that LogRequest message correctly.
我们来看看我前面提到的这个APPENDENTRIES函数
Let's look at this APPENDENTRIES function that I just mentioned.
当检查并确定log符合要求后 我们就会调用APPENDENTRIES函数
So, APPENDENTRIES here is called if we have checked that the log is OK.
我们想把LogRequest消息中的新log项
And we want to append the new entries from the LogRequest message
追加进从节点的log中
to the follower’s log.
我们现在要做的第一件事情是进行检查
And so, the first thing we now need to check is,
有可能出现的一种情况是
well, it could be that
从节点已经持有了此条消息中的一些log项
the follower already has some of the log entries that are contained within this message.
如果出现这种情况 我们需要检查这些log项是否相同
And if so, we need to check whether those are the same.
首先 如果suffix部分非空
So, first of all, if the suffix is non-empty,
这意味着LogRequest消息的确包含新的log项
so, that means the LogRequest message did contain new log entries,
且如果从节点的log长度（log.length）大于prefixLen
and if the length of the follower’s log is longer than the prefixLen,
也就是说 从节点的一些log项已经超过了prefix部分的log项
so, that is, the follower already has some log entries that go beyond the prefix,
此时 新的log项 也就是suffix部分的log项
so, at this point, we have the suffix, the new log entries
与从节点已经持有的log项存在一些重叠
overlapping with the log entries that the follower already has.
这种情况下 我们将找到从节点与主节点
In that case, we're going to find the last log entry that we can compare
可以对比的最后一个log项所在的位置
between the follower’s state and the leader’s state.
可比较的最后一个log项位置
And that's going to be
或者等于从节点的log.length-1
either the log.length-1,
或者等于prefixLen+suffix.length-1
or it's going to be the prefixLen+suffix.length-1，
取这两个值的较小值
whichever of those two is smaller.
这就是我们要比较的log项所对应的索引值
And that is going to be the index of the log entry that we're going to compare.
对于这个特定的索引值 我们将比较
And for that particular index, we are going to compare
从节点log项的任期数
the term number in the follower’s log
和新log项 也就是从主节点收到的suffix部分
to the term number in the corresponding entry in the suffix, in the new log entries,
对应log项的任期数
that we received from the leader.
如果这两个log项的任期数不相同
And if those are not the same term number,
这意味着log项存在不一致的情况 我们需要截断从节点的log项
that means we have an inconsistency in the log, and we have to truncate the log.
我们接下来要做的是
And so, what we're going to do then is
只保留从节点截至prefixLen的log项
to actually keep only the follower’s log up to prefixLen,
我们把从节点所有超过prefixLen的log项都扔掉
and everything beyond prefixLen, we're going to throw away.
这么做是正确的
That is the correct thing to do here,
因为前面的log项可能来自于前面的主节点
because those previous log entries might have come from a previous leader,
且这些log项还没有被提交
and they will not yet be committed.
Raft要保证的一个关键性质是 如果一个log项已被提交
So, a key property that Raft ensures is that if a log entry is committed,
则此log项将不会被修改 也不会被丢弃
then it will never change, and it won't be discarded,
此log项不会因为这里的截断操作而被移除
and it won't be removed by this truncation process here.
但如果一个log项尚未被提交
But a log entry that is not yet committed,
则此log项有可能被这里的截断操作移除
it could happen that that log entry gets removed as part of this truncation.
如果这两个log项的任期数相同 则我前面已经解释过
So, if these term numbers are the same, then as I explained earlier
Raft会保证 包括这一特定的索引值在内
Raft guarantees that then the logs are identical
所有之前的log项也都相同
up to that point including that particular index.
这种情况下 我们不需要截断log 因为我们知道
And in that case, we don't need to truncate the logs, because we know that
主节点的log和从节点的log是一致的
the leader’s log and the follower’s log are consistent with each other.
无论我们是否会截断log
Either way, regardless of whether we need it to truncate or not,
我们现在都要把新的log项追加进从节点的log中
we can now append any new log entries to the log.
这里有可能出现的情况是
And so, it could be now here that
suffix部分包含从节点已经持有的一些log项
the suffix contains some log entries that the follower already has,
此时 我们就不需要追加这些log项了
in which case, we don't need to append them again.
我们将suffix部分中从节点尚未持有的第一个log项开始
And we're just going to start off with the first entry in the suffix
把从这里开始的log项追加进从节点的log中
that the follower does not already have.
我们一直追加到suffix部分的最后一个log项
And we go up to the last entry in the suffix.
我们把这些log项依次追加进从节点的log中
And we append each of them to the follower's log.
这里有一个叫leaderCommit（主节点确认）的变量
Now comes a variable called leaderCommit.
我之前没有介绍过这个变量的含义
I've not talked about this very much yet.
但当我们讨论提交log项时 这个变量就变得非常重要了
But this will become important now when we talk about committing log entries.
leaderCommit是一个整数 它告诉我们…
The leaderCommit is just an integer, and it tells us…
这个leaderCommit变量
This leaderCommit variable,
包含在主节点发来的LogRequest消息中
this came as part of the LogRequest message from the leader,
commitLength是从节点存储的一个变量
commitLength is a variable that is stored under a follower.
这个变量追踪了
And it keeps track of
自启动开始 从节点已经提交的log项总数量
how many log entries counted from the start of the log have we committed so far.
如果主节点已经提交的log项总数量
And if the number of log entries that the leader has committed
大于从节点已经提交的log项总数量
is greater than the log number of log entries that the follower has committed,
这意味着从节点可以准备提交更多的log项了
that means more log entries are ready to be committed.
因此 是否可以提交一个log项是由主节点决定的
So, it's the leader that decides when a log entry can be committed
决定方法是增加leaderCommit变量的值
by increasing this leaderCommit variable.
如果leaderCommit更大
And so, if this leaderCommit is greater,
这意味着从节点可以从commitLength开始的索引值取出log项
that means we can now take the log indexes starting from commitLength
一直取出到leaderCommit-1对应的log项
and all the way up to leaderCommit-1.
这些log项都准备好被提交了
And those are ready to be committed.
具体提交过程是
And to commit means,
首先 从节点将commitLength更新为包含新提交的log项索引值
here, first of all, we set the commitLength to include those indexes,
随后 从节点将这些消息传递给应用
and also, we deliver those messages to the application.
这就是从节点传递全序顺序广播消息的位置
So, this is now the total order broadcast delivery as it happens on the followers.
下一页幻灯片将单独介绍主节点传递全序顺序广播消息的位置
The total broadcast delivery on the leader happens separately on the next slide.
这就是从节点涉及的所有操作了
So, that is actually all that happens on the followers.
我们讲完了从节点视角下的故事
So, that's completed the story from the point of view of the followers.
我们只需要再讲完主节点视角下的故事
We just need to finish the story from the point of view of the leader.
如果你还记得
And so, if you remember,
从节点在这里给主节点发送回了一个LogResponse消息
here the followers sent a LogResponse message back to the leader, telling it
告诉主节点 从节点是否接受了新的log项并追加进自己的log中
whether the follower was able to accept the new log entries and append them to the log.
在这里
And this is now
当主节点从从节点收到这些LogResponse消息后
when the leader receives those LogResponse messages from the follower,
主节点现在需要决定哪些log项已经准备好被提交了
and now the leader needs to decide which log entries are ready to be committed.
如果一个log项已经被系统中的多半quorum节点确认
So, a log entry is ready to be committed
则这个log项就已经准备好被提交了
if it's been acknowledged by a quorum of nodes in the system.
当主节点收到其中一个LogResponse消息时
When the leader receives one of these LogResponse messages,
和之前收到一条消息的处理过程一样
as always when receiving a message,
主节点第一件要做的事情是检查任期数
the first thing it has to do is check the term number.
如果LogResponse消息中的任期数大于主节点当前的任期数
So, if the term number in the LogResponse message is greater than the leader's term,
这意味着系统中出现了持有更高任期数的新节点
that means, oh, there's a new node with a higher term number.
和之前一样 主节点必须接受此任期数 将自己转变为从节点状态
As always, we have to accept that term number and transition to follower state,
忘记上一任期中自己给哪个节点投了票 取消选举计时器
forget whoever we voted for in a previous term, and cancel the election timer.
当任期数正确时
However, in the case where the term number is correct,
也就是消息中的任期数与主节点的任期数匹配
so, the term number matches the leader's term number,
且主节点现在仍然为主节点
and the leader is in fact still the leader,
主节点会继续往下
then it can go ahead.
主节点需要先检查success字段是否为true
Now, first, it has to check was the success field true.
这个success字段指的是主节点收到的从节点LogResponse消息中
So, this is the success field in the LogResponse message
所包含的success字段
that it received from the follower.
如果success字段为true
And if this success field is true,
且此消息中包含的确认值（ack）
and if the acknowledgement that was contained in that message
至少等于相同从节点之前已经确认过的确认值
is at least the number that was previously acknowledged by the same follower,
这意味着从节点正在确认新的消息
that means the follower’s acknowledging new messages now.
如果消息没有按照顺序传递 则现象是
If the messages get delivered out of order, it could happen that
具有较高ack值的消息先被传递 具有较低ack值的消息后被传递
a message with a higher act is delivered first, and then a message with a lower act later.
因此 这将保证无论消息按照何种顺序传递
So, this ensures that no matter which order the messages are delivered,
每个节点都会按照相同的顺序传递
everything ends up being fine.
如果判断结果和我们期待的一样
So, in the expected case, where the acknowledgement
即ack值大于等于之前的ack值
is greater than whatever the previous acknowledgement was,
主节点可以判断
the leader can now record the fact that
它收到了此特定从节点的确认信息 主节点把确认信息记录下来
it has received an acknowledgement from this particular follower.
记录的方法是
And it does this
将sentLength变量和actedLength变量都更新为ack值
by updating both the sentLength variable and the actedLength variable to be that integer
也就是更新为此特定从节点已确认的log项数量
that is, the number of acknowledged log entries from that particular follower.
随后 主节点调用COMMITLOGENTRIES（确认日志项）函数
And it then calls the COMMITLOGENTRIES function
函数描述在下一页幻灯片中
which will be on the next slide
从而确认哪些log项已经准备好被提交了
to actually decide which log entries are ready to be committed.
另一方面 如果LogResponse没有成功
On the other hand, if this LogResponse was not successful,
我们必须要检查sentLength
then we have to check the sentLength.
如果LogResponse没有成功 有种情况是主节点和从节点的log项存在缺口
And so, if it was not successful, it could be that there was a gap in the log.
大家还记得 我们把log拆分为prefix部分和suffix部分
So, remember, we split the log into a prefix and a suffix,
我们假设从节点持有prefix部分的所有log项
the prefix we assumed the follower already has.
但如果从节点丢失了其中一部分log项呢？
But what if the follower lost part of its log?
如果是这样 则log项存在缺口 从节点未持有所有prefix部分的log项
And there's actually a gap and it doesn't have the entire prefix.
这一部分代码就是处理这种情况的
That's the case that we handle here.
如果是因为这种情况使得LogResponse没有成功
So, in this case, if the success was not true,
我们要递减从节点的sentLength变量
then the sentLength variable for the follower, we're just going to decrement that.
我们要把从节点的sentLength变量减1
So, we're going to reduce it by 1,
这意味着我们要把prefix部分的长度缩小1
and that means now we're going to shrink the length of the prefix by 1,
我们要在下一次尝试中 向此从节点多发送一个log项
and we're going to send one more log entry to the follower on our next attempt.
如果从节点和主节点持有的log项
Now, if there's a large gap between
存在巨大的缺口
what the log that the follower has and the log that the leader has,
这个过程会被多次迭代
this could take quite a few iterations
我们在每次迭代中只把prefix部分的长度减小1
where we just reduce the length of the prefix by 1 every single time.
你可能会想象出更高效的处理方法
So, you could imagine more efficient ways of doing this,
但我们现在先按照简单的方式处理
but for now, we're just going to keep it.
这个算法已经足够复杂了 我们不要再让算法变得更加复杂
It's complicated enough as it is. We're not going to over complicate it.
主节点只把sentLength减1
And we're just going to reduce this sentLength by 1,
随后 主节点再次调用REPLICATELOG函数
and then, call the REPLICATELOG function again.
大家还记得 我们之前见过了REPLICATELOG函数
Remember, we saw REPLICATELOG earlier.
这个函数的目的是向此从节点发送sentLength之后的所有log项
And this is going to send all of the log entries that go beyond this sentLength.
这样就可以保证 我们最终总可以抹平log项缺口
And so, this will ensure that eventually, we will fill in any gap in the log,
并保证从节点最终能够接受新的log项
and eventually, the follower will be able to apply the new log entries,
因为主节点可以通过这一过程把所有缺失的log项都发送给从节点
because we've sent all of the missing log entries from the leader to the follower.
这就是主节点的处理过程了 最后还差的是COMMITLOGENTRIES函数
OK, and that is the leader side except for the COMMITLOGENTRIES function.
这是我们要学习的最后一个函数了
So, that's the last one that we need to look at.
这个函数会查看actedLength变量
And this one here, it's now looks at this actedLength variable.
大家还记得 actedLength变量
Remember, in the actedLength variable,
记录了从每个从节点收到的
we recorded for every follower the number of log entries that
已经确认的log项数量
that follower has confirmed as having received.
因此 我们这里从commitLength开始循环
And so, here we are now going to start off with the variable commitLength.
commitLength是从log最开始到现在
So, that is, commitLength is the number of log entries
系统所有节点已经提交的log项数量
counted from the start of the log that we have already committed.
现在 我们希望判断
And now, we want to see
是否存在已经准备好提交的新log项
if there are any additional log entries that are also ready to be committed.
只要commitLength小于log.length
And so, as long as commitLength is less than log.length,
我们就先把acks初始化为0
we initialize acks to 0,
这个acks变量将记录 包括从节点和主节点在内
and then this acks variable will count from how many nodes,
有多少个节点
from how many followers and also the leader,
已经确认了此log项
we have an acknowledgement.
我们将遍历系统中的所有节点
And so, we are going to go through all of the nodes in the system,
包括主节点和所有的从节点
the leader and all of the followers,
我们将检查每个节点的actedLength变量
and we're going to check the actedLength variable for each of those nodes.
如果actedLength大于commitLength
And if its value is greater than the commitLength,
这意味着从这个特定节点的视角看
then that means from the point of view of that particular node,
它认为可以向前推进commitLength了
it's OK to move the commitLength forward.
也就是说 此节点已经确认了比commitLength更多的log项
So, it has already acknowledged more log entries beyond the existing commitLength.
我们把这个节点记录为已确认
And so, we're going to count that as an acknowledgement.
现在 我们要查看索引值为commitLength的log项
And now, we're going to see if the number of acknowledgments
所收到的确认数量
that we've received for the log entry at index commitLength,
如果确认数量达到多半 则这个log项就可以被提交了
if that is greater than a majority, then it's ready for that log entry to be committed.
这种情况下 我们就将传递索引值为commitLength的log项
And so, in this case, we're now going to do the total order broadcast delivery
这样就保证了此消息的传递满足全序顺序广播要求
of the message at the log entry with index commitLength.
主节点就是在这里将这条消息传递给应用的
That's going to be delivered to the application. This is on the leader.
我们将递增commitLength变量的值
And we're going to increment the value of the commitLength variable.
在我们下次调用REPLICATELOG函数时
And this new variable will then be sent out to all of the followers
我们会将这个变量发送给所有的从节点
the next time we call the REPLICATELOG function.
我们继续执行这个循环
And so, we keep going around this loop here,
只要quorum节点超过多半 我们就提交log项
and committing log entries as long as we can reach this majority quorum.
如果在某一时刻 我们发现
If at some point, then we reach the point
某个log项没有得到多半quorum节点的确认
where we don't have a majority quorum of acknowledgements yet,
我们就跳出这个循环
then we just break out of the loop,
因为这意味着在提交更多的log项之前
because that means we have to wait for more LogResponse messages
我们必须等待更多的LogResponse消息
before we can do further commits.
介绍完毕
And that's it.
这就是完整的Raft公式算法
That is the entirety of the Raft consensus algorithm.
我希望大家能跟得上
I hope you were able to follow it.
我知道算法包含了大量的细节 但我认为
I know it's a huge amount of detail, but I thought
理解主节点和从节点之间的交互过程真的很有趣
it's really interesting to see that interplay between the leaders and the followers,
比如各个节点总要检查任期数之类的
always having to check the term number, and so on.
你可以看到 共识算法如何通过仔细排序所有信息
But you can see by very carefully sequencing all of the things,
才实现的全序顺序广播
it is possible to actually achieve something like total order broadcast.
这就是本节课的内容了 下节课再见
That's all for this lecture. See you next time.